Finding Aid for Rocking the Boat...Interviews and research materials, 1930-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rocking the Boat ...Interviews and research materials 1930-2001 1992-1998
O'Farrell, Brigid
1 linear feet
0175 Aa 2
Transcripts of interviews and research material accumulated in preparation for the book, Rocking the Boat: Union Women's Voices, 1915-1975. Transcripts include interviews with Dorothy Haener, Maida Springer-Kemp, Carmen Lucia, Ah Quon McElrath, and Esther Peterson.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated to the library by Brigid O'Farrell, co-editor of Rocking the Boat (donor no. 9146 ) in 2001.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
In 1975, Joyce Kornbluh initiated the oral history project "The Twentieth Century Trade Union Woman: Vehicle for Social Change" through the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations at the University of Michigan. This project compiled interviews of women involved with the labor movement between 1900 and 1970. One of the interviewers during this project was Brigid O'Farrell, then with the Women's Research Center at Wellesley College. The desire to reach a broader audience with the information and insights provided by the interviews brought O'Farrell and Kornbluh together in the early 1990s to begin work on a book that would accomplish this goal. The book, Rocking the Boat: Union Women's Voices, 1915-1975, combines interviews conducted during that original oral history project with follow-up interviews conducted by O'Farrell and Kornbluh in the early 1990s into an edited volume that highlights some of the many faces involved with the labor movement of the 20th century.
This collection contains transcripts of interviews and research materials used in the editing of Rocking the Boat: Union Women's Voices, 1915-1975. The records have been divided into four series; Transcripts, Background Materials, Miscellaneous, and Audio/Visual Materials.
Subjects:
O'Farrell, Brigid.; Rocking the boat.; Women labor union members--United States--History--20th century.
Contributors:
Haener, Dorothy, 1917-; Peterson, Esther, 1906-; Lucia, Carmen, 1902-; McElrath, Ah Quon, 1915-; Kemp, Marcia Springer.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Transcripts
  The Transcripts (0.2 linear ft.) series contains transcripts of the follow-up interviews with Dorothy Haener, Maida Springer-Kemp, Ah Quon McElrath and Esther Peterson conducted by O'Farrell and Kornbluh in the early 1990s.
  - Dorothy Haener Interview, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Maida Springer-Kemp Interview, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Carmen Lucia Interview (for women of summer), undated (Box 1)
  - Ah Quon McElrath Interview, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Esther Peterson Interview, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Rogin Lecture "Rocking the Boat: A Tribute to Women Organizers", 1996 (Box 1)
  - Anna Sullivan Interview (from Frontiers: a Journal of Women Studies; include photograph of Anna Sullivan), 1977 (Box 1)
- Background Materials
  The Background (0.5 linear ft.) series contains information about each of the women included in the book such as clippings, writings, biographies, and a small amount of correspondence.
  - Mary Callahan, 1950-1994 (Box 1)
  - Catherine Conroy, 1948-1995 (Box 1)
  - Jessie De La Cruz, 1988-1995 (Box 1)
  - Dorothy Haener, 1991-2001 (Box 1)
  - Lillian Herstein, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Carmen Lucia, 1930-1995 (Box 1)
  - Ah Quon McElrath, 1947-1994 (Box 1)
  - Ah Quon McElrath (photocopies of photographs), 1954-1980 (Box 1)
  - Fannie Allen Neal, 1987-1995 (Box 1)
  - Esther Peterson, 1945-1997 (Box 1)
  - Alice Peurala, 1979-1986 (Box 1)
  - Maida Springer-Kemp, 1952-2000 (Box 1)
  - Maida Springer-Kemp (photocopies from Schlesinger Library), 1942-1988 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous (0.1 linear ft.) series contains information relating to the release of the book, such as signed releases to use the content from the interviews and press releases and reviews of the book.
  - Permission to use photographs, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Chapter Sign-Off Forms, 1996 (Box 1)
  - "Rocking the Boat" Press Releases and Reviews, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The Audio/Visual Materials (0.2 linear ft.) series contains photographs that were used in the book and audio cassette copies of the follow-up interviews conducted by O'Farrell and Kornbluh in the 1990s.
  - Photographs for "Rocking the Boat" (Box 1)
  - Dorothy Haener Interview, 1994 (audio cassette) (Box 1)
  - Ah Quon McElrath Interview, 1994 (2 audio cassettes) (Box 1)
  - Gloria Johnson Interview (about Mary Callahan), 1994 (audio cassette) (Box 1)
  - On Target: an audio magazine with an organizing focus, featuring the segment Rocking the Boat (commentary from three of the women featured in O'Farrell's book Rocking the Boat: Union Women's Voices, 1915-1975), 1996 (audio cassette) (Box 1)
Related Material
Researchers should note that transcripts from the original interviews conducted for the oral history project "The Twentieth Century Trade Union Woman: Vehicle for Social Change" (1978-1979) are housed at the Bentley Historical Library under the title Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations, Women and Work Program.